A Guide to the James R. Brown Papers, 1957-1991
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
James R. Brown Papers, 1957-1991
The Library of Virginia
38643, 43768
4.725 cubic feet (11 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joanne J. Hughes, Victoria, British Columbia.
Biographical Information
James Robert Brown was born in Minneapolis, Minnesota on 27 February 1917. He studied law at the University of Minnesota, and then enlisted in 1942, and flew missions with the 100th Bomb Group in England. Following the war, he went back to the University of Minnesota and earned a degree in business administration. Brown was employed as a sales manager for the Nicollet Hotel in Minneapolis. He married Ella Caroline Bertheussen (b. 1917) in St. Louis Park, Minnesota on 14 December 1940. He died on 14 September 1993.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1957-1991, of James R. Brown (1917-1993) of Minneapolis, Minnesota, containing his genealogical research on the Brown family, and allied lines of Elledge, Gunnnels, Halley, Isley, Patton, Sandusky, and Shanks. Areas covered include Fairfax County, Virginia, and Indiana, Kentucky, Minnesota, Missouri, Oklahoma, and Wisconsin. There are abstracts and copies of census records, deeds, estate administration records, marriage records and vital statistics, military records, and wills, and also correspondence, family group sheets, genealogical charts and pedigrees, genealogies compiled by others, and published sources. There is also a copy of Century Bombers: The Story of the Bloody Hundredth written by Richard Le Strange, with Brown's assistance, and published in 1989.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence.
Series II. Family Name Files.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 1-4)
  The correspondence contains requests by Brown for records from various libraries and archival repositories, historical societies, and courthouses. There are also letters to and from family members and other researchers, and responses from individuals to queries by Brown that were published in the journal Genealogical Helper.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1957. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1958. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1959. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1960 (January-June). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1960 (July-December). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1961. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1962. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1963. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1964. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1966. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1967 (January-June). (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1967 (July-October). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1967 (November-December). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1968 (January-June). (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1968 (July-September). (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1968 (October-December). (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1969 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1969 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1970 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1970 (July-September). (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1970 (October-December). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1971 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1971 (March-July). (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1971 (August-December). (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1972 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1972 (March-April). (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1972 (May-December). (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1973 (January-March). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1973 (April-December). (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1974. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1975. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1976 (January-February). (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1976 (March-December). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1977 (January-April). (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1977 (May-December). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1978 (January-February). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1978 (March-December). (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1979. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1980. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1981 (January-May). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1981 (June-December). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1982. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1983. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1984. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1985. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1986. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1987. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1988. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1989. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1990. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1991. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Allen, Patricia Joan Kirchherr. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - May, George S. (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - Rutherford, Kenneth. (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
- Series II. Family Name Files., Extent: 7 boxes. (Box 5-11)
  The family name files include Brown's research notes, and copies and abstracts of census records, deeds, estate administration records, marriage records and vital statistics, military records, and wills, and also correspondence, family group sheets, genealogical charts and pedigrees, genealogies compiled by others, and published sources. There is also a copy of Century Bombers: The Story of the Bloody Hundredth written by Richard Le Strange, with Brown's assistance, and published in 1989.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Aldridge. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ancestor Charts - Minnesota Historical Society. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Ancestry of James Shanks of Huron County, Ohio" by Harry S. Blaine. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "And Then There Were Collinsons" by Irma S. Harper. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Barnes. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Boone. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bowman. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Brown. (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Brown, Alexander (1809-1896). (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - Century Bombers: The Story of the Bloody Hundredth. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
  - Charts - Oversize. (Box Oversize PP Box 105)
  - Coe. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Cohee and Collison" by Hilda Chance. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Collison. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Computer Discs. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Corwin. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Culver. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Demarest. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dillon. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dinwiddie. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Dobbins. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Doty. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dyer. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Elledge. (Box 6, Folder 13-15)
  - Estate of Mary Holley (Macon County, MO). (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Family Group Sheets - Various Families. (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
  - "Genealogy of the Shanks Family in America" by Maj. Gen. David C. Shanks. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Gevedon. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Griffin. (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Guffey. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Gunnels. (Box 7, Folder 6-12)
  - Halley. (Box 7, Folder 13-16)
  - Halley. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Halley/Holley. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Halley (Linda Kay Hocker). (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Halley-Simpson. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Halliburton. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Hawley/Halley/Holley (Ann H. Mack). (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Hopps-Nason. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Inskeep. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Isley. (Box 8, Folder 9-13)
  - "James Shanks Memorial" by Sylvia Richards. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Johnson. (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
  - Johnston. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Kelley. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Marshall-Saltzgiver-Hansen. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - McClure. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Miller. (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Minner. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Monroe County, OH - History. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Monroe County, OH Map - Search Requests. (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Nunnely. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Patton. (Box 9, Folder 11-13)
  - Peyton. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Photographs. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Pierson. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Problem Files. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Roach. (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Rosenbush. (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Ross. (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Sadowski. (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Sandusky. (Box 9, Folder 22-24)
  - Sandusky. (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Schnepp. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Schnepp/Snepp. (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Shanks. (Box 10, Folder 6-15)
  - Sharp. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Some Descendants of James Halley, Sr. and Elizabeth Simpson". (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Some Early Settlers of the St. Croix Valley" by Mary J. Williams. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Title Abstracts - Lindsay, Garvin County, OK. (Box 11, Folder 4)